Hi, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and welcome
to my Practice Problem series.
So with Practice Problem series, we're
gonna go through some more advanced
problems that help you solve your
general chemistry homework, and try
to figure out different problems
that are combining different concepts
found throughout my videos and those
from your classes in chemistry.
So this one we're gonna really be
focusing on how equilibrium and
solutions and molarity are all gonna be
mixing together in practice problems.
So we're gonna be going through a
series of three different major practice
problems that are gonna be varying in
difficulty from introductory chemistry
to all the way to general chemistry two,
just so you can kind of see what some
of these are going to be coming across.
So there are a lot of different
types of problems that you
can come across in these.
But the biggest ones are really
gonna be calculating K values.
So those equilibrium constants, whether
it's Keq, Kc, Ka, Kb, Ksp, right?
There's all kinds of these.
The other thing is looking at, alright,
based on that value, how does it, what
side of the reaction does it favor?
Is it reactant focus
or is a product focus?
And that has to do with the K,
how big or small that K value is.
The last thing that we're gonna be really
looking at is writing solubility products,
which is, uh, Ksp, which really sees is
something soluble when you throw it in.
So if you take a solid, you throw it
into a solution, does it break apart?
And we're gonna actually go through a
general chemistry two concept, which are
preview of future videos, um, that will
eventually come in the years to come.
So, uh, other videos that we're
gonna, one other question we're
gonna look at is calculating
concentrations at equilibrium as well.
So how can we try to look at these
problems and calculate a concentration?
So if you're trying to figure out,
if you only are interested in one of
these problems, don't forget, you can
use a little, little, uh, scroll wheel
down below with the labeled chapters,
the Find Your Practice Problem.
They are labeled for
you to easily find them.
Um, hopefully this video helps
and stay tuned and please hit
that like and subscribe button for
future videos on different topics
and for future practice problems.
So thank you for, for coming
here and let's get to it.
All right, let's get at it.
So, the first problem at equilibrium.
So with this problem, what we are
looking at is we have two sulfur
dioxide reacting with oxygen gas
to yield two sulfur trioxide.
So what we have is that the amount
of each gas was measured, meaning
that yeah, at equilibrium we
are able to do that in the lab.
So we have the following concentrations
of 0.35 molar of SO2, 3.25 times 10 to
the negative one molar of oxygen and 6.41
times 10 to negative two molar of SO3.
So it says calculate the Keq, so.
If this is something that you weren't
too sure about, go back to the
equilibrium video so we can set up these.
But just in brief, the one thing
that we're looking at when it
comes to K equations is it's all
about products over reactants.
Meaning that we are going to be
looking at the concentrations of
these and we are going to be raising
it, raising those different values by
their coefficients to their powers.
So let's look at this one in particular.
So if I have, I'm interested in doing
the Keq for the following problem.
Well, we have our products,
which is sulfur trioxide, so SO3.
And for that one, one thing
that you may notice is that
it has a coefficient of two.
So what that means is that we are going
to raise this to the power of two to
illustrate that it has that coefficient.
So that's going to.
Um, essentially square its
potential of colliding with other.
So twos in this reaction,
we have our reactants.
So we have SO2, and then
we also have oxygen.
And one thing you might be kind of yelling
right now at you, maybe yelling at your
monitor is like, oh wait, there is a
coefficient for SO2, so let's do that.
We are gonna put that to a power as well.
So that is what I was mentioning,
is that we need to raise these
by their coefficients when we
are writing out these values.
So the problem calls for calculating
its K value going through this.
So when we are trying to calculate
this, what we need to do is take
our values and plug them in.
So SO3 is 0.
0 6 4 1 molar.
And for SO2 we have 0.35 molar.
So let's just highlight those in
the problem to help us see that.
So, SO2 is here, and then we
have, SO3, which was here.
And then our last one is going to
be oxygen that we will put in our
oxygen value as well, and that
is going to be 0.325 and that's
going to get plugged in as well.
Then we gotta raise our SO2 to a
power, and then we can calculate Keq.
So we'll plug these into our
calculator and then we will solve it.
Get for Keq.
Is a value of 0.10 as our value
and what we need to go off three
sig figs in all of our values.
This is going to be a value of 0.103.
So what does that tell
us about looking at this?
Well, if you remember from my previous
video, in equilibrium K can either
be greater than or less than one.
With that, it tells you what the
ratio is of the concentrations.
So if K is less than one, that
means that it favors the reactants.
If it's greater than one,
it favors the products.
So in this situation, it is telling you
that based on this reaction that we have,
this is greatly favoring the reactants.
So it's favoring the left side of it,
meaning that there's more SO2 in oxygen.
Once this, this equation or
this reaction is at equilibrium.
So this is one thing to look at
for this problem on to the next.
Okay, this, let's do it.
So this next one is, what we are trying
to do is look at the following thing,
which tells you, right, the net ionic
equation for the solubility of copper
hydroxide, which what this is trying to
set up when it comes to equilibrium is
telling you that if I have a solid, let's
say, kind of like table salt, right?
So, which is something that
you've just put on food every day.
If you are to have that in your hand,
it is in the form of a solid, but if you
throw it in a glass of water quickly,
in a blink of an eye, it will, it will
dissolve and vanish before your eyes.
This is what this is trying to ask
you is if I have something like copper
hydroxide where this is a copper salt,
which is a solid, what would happen
when that is thrown into solution?
When it goes in, it's going to
dissolve into its most basic ions.
So the first one being copper two plus,
and the other one being hydroxide.
But being that this is, OH
minus with a two here, we don't
write, OH, we don't write that.
There's uh OH minus with a two subscript.
We are going to show that
as a two coefficient.
To say that, oh, this is breaking
down into its most simple
ions when this is in solution.
So being that it's breaking down
in water, these are all considered
to be aqueous as we write what is
referred to as the solubility product.
So that is what this, what these
are on the right hand side.
These are all solubility products, as
these are dissolved dissociating and
being ionized by water in solution.
So the next part is asking,
all right, write the solubility
product equilibrium expression.
A little bit of a mouthful, but
what that's asking for you is a
different form of K, which is still
products over reactance, but is Ksp?
So when we are writing our expression for
Ksp, we still do products over reactives.
So we have oh, minus as one
product, and that's gonna be
raised to the power of two.
And then we have be, we have a coefficient
of two, and then we have copper two plus.
Now the reactance is copper hydroxide.
But one thing you might remember
is that one of our rules is we
never write solids or liquids.
So being that we never write solids
or liquids, we do not include it
in this portion of the problem.
This is going to be our equilibrium value.
It stays the way it is, so we can
kind of box that portion off, and
that is our equilibrium expression.
So based on that, let's say if
I ask you the following, if the
Ksp of this, uh, solution is
1.6 times 10 to the negative 19.
Is copper hydroxide soluble?
Well, what do you mean then we just do
a whole entire solubility expression?
Well, based on the K value that
tells you how soluble is something.
Is it soluble or is it relatively
insoluble or partially?
So this gives you an idea of if you look
at the reaction, 1.6 times 10 to the
nine, first, you're gonna ask yourself,
is that greater or less than one?
And one thing you're gonna kind of see
is that K is a very much less than one.
It is very, very small.
So when that happens, that's telling
you, if I go back up to my reaction
here, that this is very much favoring
the left hand side of the reaction.
So being at that is favoring the left.
That's telling you it's mainly
existing in the form of a solid.
So this expression is
not very soluble at all.
In fact, it's 10 to the, that's 19
orders of magnitude away from one.
So you can probably say,
no, it is not soluble.
This would be a big no, this is insoluble.
So, Into a more advanced concept.
If this, if you're just here for
introductory chemistry, there's some
little math skills that might be
useful here that are worth watching,
but if you're not, if you're not
here for this, this will not be
in the introductory chem class.
This will be in general chemistry two.
So let's try to make
this one step farther.
If I ask you the following, if
I have, based on the information
that we had before, so the K S P
was 1.6 times 10 and negative 19.
We know that it's equal to copper in
solution times, hydroxide in solution.
So what if I ask you, what
is the copper concentration?
How would you figure that out?
Well, we have all the piece of
information that we need and how?
How could that be?
Well, one thing that we can do is
that these are all particles that are
all pretty hard to tell apart, right?
All particles are really tiny.
And they're indistinguishable based on the
theories that we've looked at in the past.
So one, and this is a basic
general chemistry assumption
we like to make often.
So if we say that where every one
of these ions, let's say if I have
copper, so which is an ion, I also
have hydroxide, which is an ion.
What we are going to do with them is
all assume that they all equal just a
common variable that we haven't met.
We'll just call it X.
So what we will do is if I have Ksp, And
I plug in X for copper and for hydroxide.
So now I have X times X squared and all
of that is equal to 1.6 times 10 to 19.
Well, based on algebra, this is
something that's, that you can simplify.
Being this is X times x squared.
Multiply these two things
together on both sides.
So when that happens, we can
simplify that to be X cubed.
Okay.
So being that this is now X cubed
equal to 1.6 times 10 to the
19, how can I get X by itself?
Well, the way that we can do that
is we can take a cube root of this.
So instead of a square root, it's a root
with a three power instead of each side.
And what that's going to do is cancel
out our, our cube on the left side.
So that's something that you can just
plug into a calculator when you do that.
And when you do that function,
that's gonna tell you that X,
which is the same thing as copper.
The concentration of that is
going to be equal to 5.4 times 10
to the negative seven molarity.
Okay, so, and that's going to be
your copper two plus concentration.
So this is something that if you're
taking future classes, that's a
future concept on to the next.
Okay, let's do our last
practice problem for this set.
So the Ka of the following reaction
is 1.6 times 10 to the negative
five, meaning that we have a
reaction of acetic acid, so CH3COOH.
And it's reacting with water to create
H three O plus and CH3COO minus.
So what we are seeing is an acid donating
its proton to create hydronium, and
it's making a conjugate base as well.
So what we have as we have the
reaction, the Ka value, and we have the
concentrations of acetic acid, which
is two molar, and we are given the.
Concentration of CH3COO
minus, and that is 0.25 molar.
And this is at equilibrium.
What is the concentration of
hydronium and determinants pH?
So this is combining equilibrium
with acids and bases altogether.
So how do we start it?
The first step is being that we already
have a balanced chemical reaction.
It's for us to write out the
equilibrium expression for ka.
So Ka is going to be equal to
the products over the reactants.
So we have H3O plus, then
we have CH3COO minus.
In our reactants we have
CH3COOH, and we also have water.
But one thing to remember is we
do not include water because we
never include solids or liquids.
So this will be our
equilibrium expression.
Now, from that, we were giving
a lot of different values
that we can plug into this.
The first one from above was the um,
Ka or Ka constant for this formula.
So we can plug that in.
So Ka was 1.6 times 10
to the negative fifth.
So when we plug that in, we
can now ha take our formula and
plug in all the concentrations.
So H3O plus is our variable.
We're trying to find that we can plug
in the concentration of CH3COO minus.
That was 0.25.
Was that value?
And then we also had our
concentration of acetic acid,
which was 2.0 molar as our value.
Alright, so what are we trying to do here?
Well, we have to get H3O plus by itself.
So how do you do that?
Well, this is all an algebra problem.
So the first thing that we're
gonna do is to get this by itself
is we're going to multiply.
2.0 by both sides to cancel
out the 2.0 on the bottom.
So that would be step one.
When that happens, 2.0 gets by itself.
We can simplify our number now
on the left, so that would be
3.2 times 10 to the negative.
Fifth is equal to hydronium plus and
0.25, which that was in blue before,
so let's put that in blue again.
So let's put that in the same size.
Two.
That's 0.25.
Now, how do we get hydronium by itself?
Well, being that they're both
being multiplied by each other.
The way to get them separated
is by dividing them.
So if we divide those two values
by both sides, so if I divide it
on the left and on the right, we
will get to that value by itself.
So 0.25.
These cancel out.
We'll do the same thing on the left side.
Now what that's gonna do is give
us our concentration of hydronium,
which will be 1.28 times 10 to the
negative four molar of hydronium.
So that's our concentration.
So that is one answer.
Now, if you remember from the
problem, we also had to figure out pH.
So how do we do that?
Well, that goes back to the pH and
acids and basis video, which the way
to solve for that is, if you remember,
is that pH is equal to the negative
log of the hydronium concentration.
And one thing that's a tip, if you ever
see high hydronium, that concentration
is going to be equal to what you see
for hydrogen ion, depending on how
a, how a problem is being written.
So another little tip
for a practice problem.
So when we have this, we're gonna
plug our value in to this equation.
So the, the 1.28 is going to
be plugged into this value.
So when we do that, we are going to get
a pH of 3.89 When we take the negative
log of 1.28 times 10 and negative four.
This is my last practice prom.
I hope this video helped going
through several different
examples if these helped.
Remember, this is Dr.
Dan here.
Please hit that like and subscribe
button to see future videos, and
I hope that I can help you pass
and acce your chemistry class.
Thank you so much for stopping
by, and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.